<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hello there...</title>
    <link>https://VictorBitca.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Hello there...</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://VictorBitca.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A proper OP-Z plugin prototype</title>
      <link>https://VictorBitca.github.io/posts/2019/06/a-proper-op-z-plugin-prototype/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://VictorBitca.github.io/posts/2019/06/a-proper-op-z-plugin-prototype/</guid>
      <description>Let&amp;rsquo;s be honest, previous attempt at an OP-Z plugin thingy was a failure, Main drawbacks being the boot times, all the bugs and overhead that come with running Linux &amp;amp; jack &amp;amp; supercollider on such a small machine. You just don&amp;rsquo;t need Linux if you want to run a medium complexity synth. But most importantly it kinda failed at being fun.
Teesny 3.6 and teensy audio board  With teensy 3.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding common regions in multiple audio files</title>
      <link>https://VictorBitca.github.io/posts/2019/04/finding-common-regions-in-multiple-audio-files/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://VictorBitca.github.io/posts/2019/04/finding-common-regions-in-multiple-audio-files/</guid>
      <description>Probably you&amp;rsquo;ve been binge-watching a series and those pesky intros always got in your way. The intro and outro song is already playing on repeat in your head, the visuals already burned onto your retina, you&amp;rsquo;re ready to do anything to not hear one more time that intro song.
Some streaming services like Netflix already have a skip intro button, but how does it work? Do you really think that people at Netflix in charge of their content specify in their contracts that content providers should also provide the intro/outro time range?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating an OP-Z Plugin</title>
      <link>https://VictorBitca.github.io/posts/2019/04/creating-an-op-z-plugin/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://VictorBitca.github.io/posts/2019/04/creating-an-op-z-plugin/</guid>
      <description>Where it actually started It all began almost a year ago, when I’ve been playing with my PO-20 “Arcade” and wondered what if it was hackable, maybe if it was there would also be a community around pocket operators like there is one for Canon “Magic Lantern” firmware. Well, there was no such thing. But there is OTTO, an open source project initially inspired by OP-1 but clearly going in their own direction at the moment, consider contributing if you&amp;rsquo;re interested.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://VictorBitca.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://VictorBitca.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>Well&amp;hellip; it&amp;rsquo;s a blog</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>