<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>3am engineering</title>
    <link>https://3am.engineering/</link>
    <description>Recent content on 3am engineering</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://3am.engineering/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Swift async await vs Combine: values over time</title>
      <link>https://3am.engineering/works/values-over-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://3am.engineering/works/values-over-time/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ll focus on Combine and Swift concurrency for one specific use case: a potentially infinite sequence of events that could overwhelm the consumer, or at best, merely waste resources by generating excessive values that the consumer might not even require.
The values from these sequences cannot be dropped using debounce or throttle operators, as is typically done with certain UI events, thus, the need for proper backpressure support.
Subscription and Task cancellation An important aspect from an ergonomic standpoint is the lifecycle management of an entity that could potentially emit an infinite number of values.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ultra Detailed Topographic CNC Carvings</title>
      <link>https://3am.engineering/works/detailed-topographic-cnc-sculptures/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://3am.engineering/works/detailed-topographic-cnc-sculptures/</guid>
      <description>Mount St. Helens hillshade
This article might get too technical in places with all the CNC, CAM, CAD, GIS terminology. To spare your time here&amp;rsquo;s the TLDR:
TLDR More than 6 month ago something clicked and I got all enthusiastic about maps and topography. 2D renders were all nice and cool but real 3D topographic sculpts would really elevate the data to a higher level.
Turns out it&amp;rsquo;s hard to make detailed models and there are quite a few reasons why nobody (at least documented online) seems to have a solid working process or a comercial product that isn&amp;rsquo;t just a 2D print.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Custom force-feedback controller and next gen predictions</title>
      <link>https://3am.engineering/works/custom-haptic-feedback-controller-ffb/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://3am.engineering/works/custom-haptic-feedback-controller-ffb/</guid>
      <description>TL;DR I wanted a controller specifically made for racing sim games, with force feedback like on the big expensive sim racing wheels, so I made one.
One is a bit different than the others
The Inspiration The new PS5 controller with its haptics and adaptive triggers marks the dawn of a new era.
Adaptive triggers internals, isn&amp;rsquo;t that cool?
What even is FFB? and why it makes things better? Maybe the industry will move towards an &amp;ldquo;FFB all the things&amp;rdquo; approach, maybe not, let&amp;rsquo;s test it out and see its pros and cons.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Metalens for Hacker News</title>
      <link>https://3am.engineering/works/metalens-hacker-news-ios-client/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://3am.engineering/works/metalens-hacker-news-ios-client/</guid>
      <description>Update: The app is now open source The app is no longer on AppStore, a cleaned-up and rewritten version is now available on GitHub
Download it on the app store TL;DR: If you downloaded the app don&amp;rsquo;t forget to toggle the Safari switch in Settings
The &amp;ldquo;Do something with Hacker News&amp;rdquo; idea Searching for HN clients on the app store results in many reasonable looking apps. Some of them abandoned a few years back, others look like a developer needed at least one random published app to apply for the job.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://3am.engineering/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://3am.engineering/about/</guid>
      <description>Hello! I&amp;rsquo;m Victor Bitca.
I&amp;rsquo;m a software engineer, usually working on iOS apps or some custom tooling. This blog focuses on other engineering challenges and projects that I found engaging and fun.
Feel free to contact me at victor.bitca.development at gmail.com</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A proper hardware plugin for the OP-Z synth</title>
      <link>https://3am.engineering/works/opz-modular-synth-plugin/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://3am.engineering/works/opz-modular-synth-plugin/</guid>
      <description>The, previous attempt at an OP-Z plugin thingy was a failure.
The boot time, the bugs, and overhead that come with running Linux + jack + supercollider stack on such a Raspberry Pi Zero is too much. You don&amp;rsquo;t need Linux if you want to run a medium complexity synth. But it also failed at being fun and easy to use.
Teesny 3.6 and teensy audio board
With teensy 3.6 &amp;amp; teensy audio board, the boot times are around a second or less, it&amp;rsquo;s faster than the OP-Z!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Skip that intro! - Matching audio segments in multiple files</title>
      <link>https://3am.engineering/works/audio-fingerprinting-matching-track-sections/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://3am.engineering/works/audio-fingerprinting-matching-track-sections/</guid>
      <description>If you ever binge-watched a series you should already be familiar with the urge to skip ASAP that intro/outro song.
Many streaming services already have a skip intro button, but how does it work? Did you think that the content partners need to specify timestamps for intro/outros at the content ingest stage? That would be too easy.
I attempted to automate the intro detection with chromaprint mostly for fun because it seems that was my definition of fun at the time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A hardware plugin for the OP-Z synth</title>
      <link>https://3am.engineering/works/opz-hardware-sampler-plugin/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://3am.engineering/works/opz-hardware-sampler-plugin/</guid>
      <description>2019 Update Half of this article is irrelevant now, OP-Z can sample from USB or the mic and supports custom synth engines (kinda) after some updates.
Background Since I got my hands on the PO-20 “Arcade” I wanted to write custom firmware for it. Of course that wasn&amp;rsquo;t possible.
The next best thing was the OTTO inspired by OP-1. I considered joining the project for a moment but writing most of the components from scratch would take years to reach a v.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://3am.engineering/metalenspolicy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://3am.engineering/metalenspolicy/</guid>
      <description>Privacy Policy This policy applies to all information collected or submitted on the Metalens app for iOS devices. If you choose to use Metalens, then you agree to the collection and use of information concerning this policy.
Information we collect Metalens collects anonymous statistics such as crash reports and anonymized feature usage statistics. Metalens does not use third-party services that may collect information used to identify you.
Ads and analytics Metalens does not serve ads.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://3am.engineering/metalensterms/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://3am.engineering/metalensterms/</guid>
      <description>Metalens Terms and Conditions of Use 1. Terms By accessing this Website, accessible from 3am.engineering, you are agreeing to be bound by these Website Terms and Conditions of Use and agree that you are responsible for the agreement with any applicable local laws. If you disagree with any of these terms, you are prohibited from accessing this site. The materials contained in this Website are protected by copyright and trade mark law.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
